<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The resurrection of loyalty and obedience, out of the grave of rebellion by the sacred force of the oathes of supremacy and allegiance, which have lain as dead, and out of minde, for diverse years, and here raised up out of the dust, and discovered in their great inviolable force and power unto the people : for the humbling of those that are guilty of the breach of them, the quelling of rebellious principles, and excitement unto the duties of obedience and subjection, according to the tenor of the said oathes.</title>
            <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17512953</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17512953</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67636)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1107:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The resurrection of loyalty and obedience, out of the grave of rebellion by the sacred force of the oathes of supremacy and allegiance, which have lain as dead, and out of minde, for diverse years, and here raised up out of the dust, and discovered in their great inviolable force and power unto the people : for the humbling of those that are guilty of the breach of them, the quelling of rebellious principles, and excitement unto the duties of obedience and subjection, according to the tenor of the said oathes.</title>
                  <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Mabb, for William Shears ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106525:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106525:1"/>
            <p>THE Reſurrection of <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> out of the Grave of REBELLION: By the ſacred Force of the Oathes of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which have lain as dead, and out of minde, for diverſe years; and here raiſed up out of the duſt, and diſcovered in their great inviolable Force and Power unto the PEOPLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Humbling of thoſe that are Guilty of the Breach of them; The quelling of Rebellious Principles, and excitement unto the Duties of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Subjection, according to the Tenor of the ſaid OATHES.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>I counſell thee to keep the Kings Commandment, and that in regard of the Oath of God.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 8.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>And all the Congregation made a Covenant with the King in the Houſe of God, and he ſaid unto them. Behold, the Kings Sonne ſhall Reign, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Chron. 23 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>For the tranſgreſſion of a land, many are the Princes thereof, but by a man of understanding and knowledge, the ſtate thereof ſhall be prolong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Proverb. 28.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Mabb,</hi> for <hi>William Shears</hi> in <hi>Bedford</hi> ſtreet neer <hi>Coven-Garden,</hi> at the <hi>Blew Bible,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106525:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106525:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To His Eccellencie the Lord Generall <hi>Monck,</hi> General of all the Forces of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> The reviver of the dying hopes of theſe diſtreſſed Nations, and of the afflicted Churches therein.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellency,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF the Lord were as forgetfull of our Obligations as we are, or if he did remember our ſins no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than we do remember duties: or if our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibleneſſe of our iniquities were the cure of our maladies; or if there were any ſecurity to our ſouls in our ſecurity, in our tranſgreſſions; I might expect with ſome juſtice to be cenſured, as troubleſome and impertinent, in going about to revive theſe Oathes, that have lain ſo long for dead in theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and have been for ſo many years buried in the grave of Oblivion; or to amaze or diſquiet the Nation with the noiſe and the clamour of them: but when I have conſidered how dangerous it is for peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſleep by the Devils <hi>Opium,</hi> and how much better it is, that a people ſhould be troubled, than that they ſhould be deſtroyed; and that they ſhould be deſturbed out of their moſt pleaſant ſlumbers and dreams, than that they ſhould enjoy their quiet with the dreadfull flames of Gods wrath and indignation, menaced againſt a perjured People about their ears,
<pb facs="tcp:106525:3"/>ready to ſeize upon them, both to their temporal and eternal deſtruction. I cannot but conclude it to be much ſafer for them, and much more tolerable unto them, to be awaked to Repentance, by the voice of theſe Oathes, and by the diſcovery of the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that thereby lyes upon this Nation; and of the grievous ſins that have been committed, and are ſtill too much juſtified againſt them, than that they ſhould be awaked by the ſurprizal of that dreadfull judgment of God, which hangs over them for ſuch high tranſgreſſions. The law of Oathes, is one of the moſt awfull, and moſt inviolable precepts that God hath given to the world, and may ſeem to have as much of the fire of Mount <hi>Sinah</hi> in it, as any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of either Table. The ſecond Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement hath indeed a dreadfull ſtream and floud of flaming wrath running down upon the tranſgreſſors of it, from generation to generation; but it is allay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as it were, with a flood of mercy, unto thoſe that love the Lord, and ſhew their love in obedience thereunto.</p>
            <p>The fifth Commandment, which is the Command of obedience unto thoſe powers, that God hath ſet over us in the world, which is the importance of theſe Oathes, is the firſt Commandment, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and ſweetned with the aſſurance of Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, upon thoſe that ſhall perform their duties there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. But the third Commandement is fortified with a wall of fire; wherein God threatneth not to hold them guiltleſſe, that taketh his name in vaine. The offence whereof, is moſt grievouſly committed in the dreadfull and hainous ſins of perjury, which is
<pb facs="tcp:106525:3"/>the mark of that flying rowle and curſe, that goeth forth over the face of the whole earth, to conſume thoſe that offend therein, <hi>Zech.</hi> 5.2, 3, 4. in ſo much (that as <hi>Wonarinus</hi> obſerveth, out of the Book of the Jews, concerning the regative Precept) they were wont to terrifie thoſe that were to take an Oath with theſe expreſſions, <hi>Scito totum orbem horruiſſe in illâ horâ in quâ Deus dixit non aſſumes nomen Dei in vanum, &amp;c.</hi> Know thou that the whol world trembled at the hour wherein God ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of God in vain:</hi> and all the ſins which are written in the law, God puniſheth according to the merit: But for this ſin of perjury, he puniſheth poſterity; the puniſhments of others ſins are ſomtimes ſuſpended, but this is ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily puniſhed. Perjury conſumeth and deſtroyeth even thoſe things which fire cannot conſume: Since therefore there is ſo much danger in the ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt theſe Oathes; expoſing not onely to the judgement of the ſecond Commandment, as they are the moſt horrid ſort of ſins againſt that, and to the forfeiture of the bleſſing of the fifth Commandment, as they are ſinnes of diſobedience againſt that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; it can be no way ſafe for the people of this land, to be ſuffered to ſleep in ſuch grievous ſins: I hope therefore, there needs no further Apology to ſecure me from the juſt diſpleaſure of any, for that I have endeavoured to rouſe up the people of this Land, by the publiſhing of theſe Oathes, to a deep ſenſe of the great and hainous ſins that they lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by the violation of theſe Oathes, and to a return unto thoſe duties that they require of them: What I have done in the Explication of them, and in the
<pb facs="tcp:106525:4"/>Obſervations upon them, is in order to the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the meaning and force of them; wherein I intend not to impoſe upon the judgement of any, but deſire they may be received according to the evidence wherewith they are offered; which I hope will appear to be ſufficient, to engage unto Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for theſe evill practiſes, that have been acted in theſe Nations, and are yet ſtill on foot againſt theſe ſacred Obligations, and to better performances to the future; and to excite your Excellency, whom God hath raiſed up to be an inſtrument of his glory, and of mercy unto theſe Nations; to give your countenance to this my loyall and religious endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and your aſſiſtance to the deſired effect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Which will be a means not onely to encreaſe your Honour amongſt men; but to bring more and more bleſſings from God, upon you and your Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; by the gracious work that you ſhall do by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering this Nation from ſo great a Sin, and from ſo great a Wrath that hangs over them for it: which is the earneſt deſire of him, who deſires to approve himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>An Humble and Faithfull Servant to your Excellency, and a ſincere Honourer of your Worthy Proceedings.</hi> T. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="oaths">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106525:4"/>
            <head>The Oaths of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance;</hi> which heretofore was taken by every Member of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and all other Perſons, before they were admitted to any Office of Truth.</head>
            <div type="oath">
               <head>The Oath of Supremacy.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I A. B.</hi> do utterly teſtify and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in my conſcience, that the Kings Highneſs is the only ſupream Governour of this Realm, &amp; of all other his Highneſs Dominions and Countries, as well in all ſpirituall and Eccleſiaſtical things (or cauſes) as temporal: and that no forreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State or Potentate hath or ought to have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny jurisdiction, power, ſuperiority, Preheminence or authority ecleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106525:5"/>or ſpiritual within this realm: and therefore I do utterly remounce and forſake all forreign jurisdiction, powers, ſuperiorities &amp; authorities, and do promiſe that from henceforth I ſhall bear faith &amp; true Allegiance to the Kings Highneſs, his heirs and lawful ſucceſſours, and (to my power) ſhall aſſiſt and defend all juriſdiction, privilege, prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and authority granted or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Kings Highneſs, his heirs &amp; ſucceſſours, and united and annexed to the imperiall Crowne of the Realm. <hi>So help me God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="oath">
               <head>The Oath of Allegiance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I A. B.</hi> Doe truly and ſincerely acknowledge, profeſſe, teſtifie and declare, in my Conſcience, before God and the World, That Our Soveraign Lord King <hi>Charles,</hi> is Lawfull and Rightfull King of this Realm, and all other his Majeſties Dominions and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106525:5"/>Countries; and that the Pope neither of himſelf, nor by any Authority of the Church or See of <hi>Rome;</hi> or by any other means (with any other) hath power or authority to Depoſe the King, or to diſpoſe any of his Majesties Kingdomes or Dominions, or to Authoriſe any Forraigne Prince to invade or annoy him or his Countries, or to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge any of his Subjects of their Allegiance and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his Majeſty; or to give licenſe or leave to any of them to bear Arms raiſe tumults, or to offer any violence or hurt to his Majeſties Royall Perſon, State, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to any of his Majeſties Subjects within his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions; Alſo I do ſwear from my heart, that notwithstanding any Declaration or ſentence of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication or deprivation, made or granted, or to be made or granted by the Pope or his ſuceſſors, or by any authority derived, or pretended to be derived from him, or his ſeed, against the ſaid King, his heirs or ſucceſſors, or any ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the ſaid subjects from their obedience: I will bear faith and true Allegiance to his Majesty, and his Heirs and Succeſſors; and him and them will defend to the uttermoſt of my power, againſt all Conſpiracies and Attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made against his or their Perſons, their Crown and Dignity, by reaſon or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of any ſuch ſentence, or declaration, or otherwiſe; and will doe my beſt endeavour to diſcloſe and make known unto his Majeſty, his Heirs, and Succeſſors, all Treaſons, and Traiterous Conſpiracies, which I ſhall know or hear of to be againſt him or any of them; and I do further ſwear, that I doe from my heart, abhor, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and abjure, as impious and Heretical, this damnable doctrine and poſition, that Princes, which be Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated and deprived by the Pope, may be Depoſed or Murthered of their ſubjects, or any other whatſoever;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106525:6"/>and I doe believe, and in my conſcience am reſolved, that neither the Pope, nor any other perſon whatſoever, hath power to Abſolve me of this Oath, or any part thereof, which I acknowledge by good and full Authority, to be lawfully ministred unto me; and doe renounce all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, and diſpenſations to the contrary; And theſe things I do plainly and ſincerely acklnowledge and ſwear, according to theſe expreſs words by me ſpoken; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the plain and common ſenſe and understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame words, without any equivocation or mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall evaſion, or ſecret reſervation whatſoever; And I do make this recognition and acknowledgment, heartily, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and truly upon the true faith of a Chriſtian; <hi>So help me God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="observations">
            <head>Some breif Obſervations concerning the Oathes of Supremacy and Allegiance.</head>
            <head type="sub">Diſcovering the great obligation that lieth upon the Conſciences of the People of this Land, binding to the performance of them, and the great and horrid Impieties that have been committed in their violation.</head>
            <p>Obſervation <hi>I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THat of all Obligations, that it is poſſible for the Creatures to lay upon themſelves, there is none more ſacred, none more inviolable, none of more dreadfull conſequence in the violation, none of greater importance to Religion towards God, or to the good and peace of humane ſociety; than an Oath. It being an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to the great God of Heaven and Earth, as a Witneſſe and a Judge of the Truth of our Aſſertions, and the fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of our Promiſes; together with an Obligation of our ſelves, to the forfeiture of his Mercy and Favour, and to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106525:6"/>the Curſe and Judgement of God upon our ſoules, in caſe we deale fraudulently and unfaithfully with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> II. That a publick Oath that is made by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Authority of a Nation, to binde the people of the Land, is of ſo great force and power, that it doth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly binde thoſe that made it, and have taken it, but alſo all the people of the Nation, and not onely thoſe that are then in being, when the ſaid Oaths were made and taken, but alſo all their ſucceeding Poſterity, that are within the deſigne, and the purpoſe of the ſaid Oaths; as doth emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently appear by the force and power that was in the Oath, which was made and taken by <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the 9. <hi>chap.</hi> of <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> which bound not onely <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and the Princes, who made and took the ſaid Oath; but alſo all the people of the land, and all their ſucceeding poſterity: as is manifeſt by comparing that paſſage in the 9. of <hi>Joſhuah</hi> with the 21. <hi>chap.</hi> of the 2. book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> from the 1. <hi>verſe,</hi> to the end of the 14 where the breach of the Oath of <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and the Princes by <hi>Saul</hi> in ſlaying of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> was puniſhed in the time of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> with three years Famine upon the land and people of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> III. That though there be many infirmities and miſcarriages committed in the making and taking of theſe publick Oathes, and although the things that they oblige unto, prove to be againſt the Intereſt of the people; and although the breach or violation thereof, hath the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of faire and ſpecious intents and ends, ſeemingly conducing unto the publick good of the people; yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all nor any of thoſe pretentions doth either make void the Obligation of thoſe Oaths, nor deliver the people from the great guilt of the ſin which is committed in the violation thereof; nor ſecure them from the dreadfull Judgment of God? As appears clearly by the ſevere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of Almighty God, in the judgement that he ſent upon the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for the breach of that Oath that was made unto the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> notwithſtanding that it was obtained by a palpable lye and falſhood, aſſumed raſhly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106525:7"/>without conſulting with God: Proved to be againſt a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection that God himſelf gave unto the people, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thoſe very <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> amongſt the reſt of the Nations that inhabited the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and expreſly prohibiting them to make any Covenant with them, or to ſhew them favour, as appears, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. and was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly againſt the conſent and intereſt of the people, and was broken by <hi>Saul,</hi> in his zeal to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> as appears, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. <hi>viz.</hi> which yet was puniſhed with ſo great a judgment, as three years Famine upon the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and could not be expiated without the deſtruction of divers of the poſterity of <hi>Saul</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> IV. That the cuſtome of Oaths made unto Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by the people, is no act of unlawfull Tyranny or Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, but hath its foundation and warrant in the word of God, as in the 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 4.17. Where <hi>Athaliah</hi> had uſurped the Kingdome, was depoſed and ſlain, and the people were engaged in an Oath and Covenant unto <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah</hi> the lawful Succeſſor in the Kingdome, by the means of <hi>Jehoiada</hi> the Prieſt: and in the 8. of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes v.</hi> 2. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience unto the King is required of the people, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Oath of God; and in the 17. of <hi>Ezekiel v.</hi> 13, 14, 15, 16. as alſo in the 18, 19, 20. <hi>verſes</hi> of the ſame Chapter, you finde God ſeverely threatning the breach of that Oath of Fidelity that was taken by <hi>Zedekiah</hi> unto the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> notwithſtanding he was an enemy to the truth of God, and a great oppreſſor of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> V. That the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance muſt needs be allowed to have in them all that ſacred force and binding power that hath been before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to binde the people of theſe Nations, and all their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding poſterity, either to the juſt and faithfull perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them, or to the undergoing of the dreadfull Judgment of Gods wrath and eternal indignation, which is invoked upon the breach of them, if it be not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by timely repentance, and that upon theſe ſeverall Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106525:7"/> 1. Becauſe theſe oaths were made &amp; taken by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick authority of theſe Nations, who in that and other publick acts did repreſent the whole people of the land.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they are not avoydable by thoſe infirmities that have been formerly noted in the oath of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which as they cannot be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto theſe Oaths, ſo neither if they were imputable unto them, would they be invalidated thereby.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe theſe oaths appears now clearly enough by the ſad conſequences of them violations not to ſtand oppoſite to the intereſt of the People, but to conduce exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereunto, and if it were otherwiſe; the validity of an Oath doth not depend upon the compliance with politick intereſt, as hath been before ſhewed, but ſtands firme and binding with a <hi>non obſtante</hi> there againſt, ſo that no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the miſtake or change of intereſt can be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in barre to the obligation of theſe Oaths.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe the force of theſe Oaths cannot die of age, no more then the Oath made unto the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> did, in all that time, which interceded between <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> but are ſtill in as great and full force and power for the binding of conſcience, as if they had been made and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken but yeſterday or this very hour.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe no ſpecious pretences of the good of the people to be obtained by the breach of them, nor fair in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of thoſe that violate them, can either juſtify them or diſcharge from their obligation, as is manifeſt in the caſe before propounded,</p>
            <p>So that by all that hath been ſaid, theſe Oaths of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and Allegiance do remain at this day in their full force and vigor, to bind the people of this land, and their poſterity unto the King and his Heirs and Succeſſours, to all intents and purpoſes, for which they were firſt made, and that under the penalty of eternal deſtruction, if they ſhall wilfully continue in the breach thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> VI. Obſerve that no ſucceeding Oath, or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Proteſtation, or Ingagement whatſoever, that doth either contradict or limit a precedent lawfull Oath, can
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106525:8"/>either be lawfully taken, or being taken, is of any force at all, either to make void, or diminiſh, or circumſcribe the force of the foregoing lawful Oath: For Oaths are not like Wills and Teſtaments, which being but the free de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of the preſent wills of them, that make them are controulable by any ſuccedent declarations, or Teſtaments, ſo that the laſt Will doth prevail againſt all that have gone before it; but Oaths and promiſes and obligations, whereby we bind our ſelves to others, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God or man, put ſuch limits and bounds upon our wills, that we have no power to contradict or limit them by any ſuccedent Oaths, or obligations whatſoever. But the firſt lawfull Oath ſtands firm and inviolable againſt all that ſhall betaken afterwards, in the whole, and in every part, and the full extent of the tenor thereof: otherwiſe an Oath were not an end of all ſtrife, as it is declared to be, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16. nor were there indeed any valid ſecurity in a promiſſory Oath, ſince a ſucceeding Oath to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or ſetting limits, conditions or exceptions to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer might renew the ſtrife, and deſtroy or diminiſh the ſecurity thereof; ſo that no Engagement, Covenant, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation or Oath of Abjuration, contrary to the Oaths of Supremacy or Allegiance can be taken, without an horrid ſin againſt God, expoſing the ſoul unto his eternall wrath. Or can it be at all of any force againſt them, though they ſhould be never ſo oft taken: neither can that limitation in the Covenant, wherein they oblige themſelves to the preſervation of the King, in the maintenance of the true proteſtant Religion, the priviledges of Parliament, and the Liberty of the Subject, limit or abate the force of thoſe abſolute obligations, whereby all Subjects are obliged to the King and his lawful Heirs and Succeſſors, which are upon them by the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance; but as ſuch limitations look very unhandſomely; ſo they have not at all any force of abatement in them, but ought to be abhord, diſclaimed &amp; rejected by all honeſt Subjects and Chriſtians, as an evil gap opened to rebellion and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to thoſe that have a mind to make ſuch an evil uſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106525:8"/>thereof, under pretence that the King doth (that which indeed he ought not to do) either depart in any thing from the true Religion, or violate the Priviledges of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or the Liberties of the Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> VII. That thoſe fore-mentioned Oathes, as they have a binding influence upon all; ſo eſpecially, do they bind thoſe, who have perſonally and ſolemnly taken them, and are enjoyned thereunto, by the laws of the Land, and muſt have a peculiar influence obligatory upon them in the execution of thoſe Offices or places, and in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thoſe Acts and Operations, which they doe by law enter upon, with the ſolemn taking of thoſe Oathes, ſo that whatever they ſhall do therein contrary thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, are not onely grievous and perjured ſins, but are to be lookt upon in religious reaſon, as utterly void, and of none effect, as thoſe wherein they exceeded their limits, and broke the bounds of that power and authority which was committed unto them, which were circumſcribed unto their operations as the ſphear of their activity, by thoſe Oaths which they took at their entrance thereupon; for it is neither religious nor reaſonable, that any man or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of men ſhould have power to act againſt the lawfull Oaths that they have taken; and then if we remember that the lawfull Members of the long Parliament, did as they were enjoyned by the law of the Nation, take the Oath of Supremacy or Allegiance, every one of them perſonally, at or before their admittance into the Houſe; and that in order to their entrance upon their power, to act as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Parlia. of <hi>England;</hi> it will be eaſie to conclude; firſt, how ſinfull, and then how altogether invalid and forceleſſe all thoſe acts that they have done, or ſhall doe, muſt needs be, which are or ſhall be any way contrary, or in the leaſt derogatory to the aforeſaid Oathes; and how great work there is for Humiliation, both to God and his ſubſtitute; for many and ſad things that have been done by ſome of them, as highly and diametrically contrary to thoſe Oathes, as it is poſſible for actions to be contrived. The cry is ſo loud, I need not inſtance; but now to come
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106525:9"/>a little cloſer to the view of theſe Oathes, and to diſcover what they import and oblige unto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> VIII. That in the firſt clauſe of the Oath of <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> the King is utterly and conſcientiouſly declared and acknowledged upon Oath, to be the onely ſupream Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of this Realm, and of all other his Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions and Countries, as well in Spiritual and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical things or cauſes as Temporal: Mark the ſupreme Governour, therefore he hath none above him, not but that he and his great Counſell together may have power to do more than he can do alone; but that none can act above him in oppoſition unto him. Secondly, The onely ſupreme Governor; therefore, there is none equall unto him: This admits of no rivall in the Throne, this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not others from Government, as his ſubordinate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments; nor doth it exclude others from being neceſſary aſſiſtants unto him in ſome acts of Government: as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of new Laws, &amp; the abrogation of thoſe that have been already made; but it doth exclude all others from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, from being inabled to act above him, or contrary unto him, or without him, or his allowance in thoſe or any other acts of Government; and this ſupremacy of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in him is ſolemnly acknowledged in this Oath (which is both a law and an Oath of the Nation) to extend unto this Realm, and to all other his Majeſties Dominions and Countries, &amp; to all Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical things &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as well as temporal; that is to ſay, as far as God hath committed either of them, unto humane &amp; ſecular powers; and as to the charge and over-ſight of religious matters, to ſee that they be rightly ordered and managed by thoſe that are the proper inſtruments of Religious Ordinances; and that the true Faith be embraced, and Religious Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties purely practiſed by the people in his Dominions and to afford his protection, defence &amp; encouragement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and to take order that the offices of the Church be rightly eſtabliſhed, and furniſhed according to the rule of God, and that wholſome laws be provided to thoſe ends, and decency and order be obſerved in Church-diſcipline,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106525:9"/>and religious performances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> IX. That wherein the ſaid Oath there is a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſclaimer &amp; renouncing of all ſpiritual or eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Juriſdiction, Power, Superiority, Preheminence, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority within this Realm; it doth reaſonably ſuppoſe that there is none within the Realm that hath any ſuch prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence above the King in thoſe matters, who is before declared to be the onely ſupream.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> X. That where the people of the Land do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe from henceforth, That is for ever to bear faith and true allegiance to the Kings Highneſs, his heires and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſucceſſors; it binds to obedience, ſubjection and fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not onely to the King in preſent being, but unto his heirs and lawful ſucceſſors, and doth bind us to them and every of them, in oppoſition to al violent uſurpers &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull intruders into the Government of this Nation, that can plead no juſt eſtabliſhment from the known and fundamentall Laws of this Nation, as are all ſuch that do either by fraud or violence intrude themſelves into the power of Govenrment.</p>
            <p>XI. Whereas this onely bindeth the people of the Land to their power (that is the utmoſt of their power) to aſſiſt &amp; defend all juriſdictions, priviledge, preheminence and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority granted or belonging to the Kings Highneſs, his heirs and Succeſſours, and united and annexed to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown of this Realm; it doth highly engage all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, Parliament-members, Generals, Commanders, Soaldiers, and all the members of this Kingdome in their ſeveral capacities, readily &amp; diligently to afford their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful help and aſſiſtance to defend the King in being from all hurt and violence, and to maintain his ſtate, govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and dignity againſt all oppoſers whatſoever, foreign or inteſtine, in like manner to defend the perſon, life, liberty of his Heirs, and lawful Succeſſors, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and aſſert the ſaid royall priviledges and prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nences unto them, and every of them, and in caſe they be fallen into any damage, or ſuffer any wrong or diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in any of them; it is then the duty unto which all people are engaged by the ſacred force of this Oath, to uſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106525:10"/>the utmoſt of their power, according to their ſeveral abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to reſtore, recover and right them againſt all force and violence under which they ſuffer, which doth pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew what is required of all people, and eſpecially of thoſe that have power in their hands at this time, for the deliverance and reſtoring of our afflicted and oppreſſed Soveraign, and how highly they are obliged thereunto; and then more eſpecially, when God doth by his ſignal and wonderfull providences admoniſh them of, and lead them on unto their duties.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="observations">
            <head>Obſervations concerning the Oath of Allegiance.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>OBſerve,</hi> That the Nation by this Oath, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, before God and the world; the power of kingly Government, is that which is eſtabliſhed by Law in this Nation; and over that and all other the Kings Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and that therfore the introducing of another form of Government, is contrary to the Law and Conſtitution of this Nation, which the people are bound to maintain.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this Regal and Kingly office is ſeated perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the King for the time being, who according to the Law of this Nation is ſaid never to die, but is preſently upon his death revived, as to this kingly right and office in him alſo, who is the next heir to the Crown.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That by the expreſs words alſo of this Oath, the Nation and the People thereof, doth not onely declare; That the ſaid King for the time being is lawful and rightful King of this Realm, and all other his Majeſties dominions and Countries, and therefore not a King of courteſy, or <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante bene placito:</hi> during pleaſure; no nor yet <hi>quamdiu ſe bene geſſerit,</hi> as long as he ſhall carry himſelf well in his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and be free from exception from the multitude, or from any others, who wil take upon them to be his Judges: for then indead he were not like to be permanent; ſince there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>hing more eaſie than for a people to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106525:10"/>that they are not well governed, as judicious Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> hath long agoe told us: and as long as there is pride and ambition, and inordinate affections in mens hearts, there will be diſcontented ſpirits amongſt a people, that will be ready to raiſe ſeditious clamours and accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt the Ruler: Beſides that a Government of a people is attended with ſo many difficulties, that there muſt needs be failings, and ſome real miſcarriages: In ſo much, that a people that will bear with no infirmities, nor miſcarriages in Governours, muſt upon the matter reſolve to endure none at all, and there is no miſcarriage equall unto that. But the King is by this Oath acknowledged and declared to have a lawful right of Government in him, and then whatſoever force is uſed to diveſt him of his power, or to diſable or bar him from the poſſeſſion or exerciſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is true violence, and the exerciſe of might againſt right, and ſuch as flyes in the face of God, who is the God of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Righteouſneſs, and the great aſſerter and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of the right of Kings, as that which is under him, the ſafeguard and ſecurity of all other inferior rights and proprieties, ſo that no ſucceſs of violent and illegall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices or enterpriſes, can be juſtly pleaded in barr againſt this Ruler, we will juſtify that frantick axiome or reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Son of <hi>Beliall,</hi> in <hi>Wiſdom c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 11. Let our ſtrength be the Law of righteouſneſs; for that which is fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is found to be nothing worth, and this right of Kings is eſtabliſht by the word of Chriſt himſelf, who is the King of Kings, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.21. and is declared to be very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the right of God. Give therefore unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and to God the things that are Gods; where the right of <hi>Caeſar</hi> is aſſerted by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, though he was an Heathen, and an enemy to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. And however that of <hi>Ezekiell</hi> 1.27. (as the verſes are numbred in our Bibles) is interpreted of the right of Chriſt. Yet it may ſeem to be applied in ſome ſort by the wonderfull operations of Divine providence in this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, at this time, unto our preſent affairs &amp; concernments, and to the buſineſs we have in hand; I will overturne, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturne,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106525:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>overturne it; untill he come whoſe right it is: and I will give it him; <hi>I</hi> am ſure it ſtareth or at leaſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth that there is a right of Government, and of the Kingly office, and this is of ſo ſtrong and adamantine a temper; that no Steel nor ſword can cut it or deſtroy it?</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is declared by this Oath, that the <hi>Pope,</hi> neither of himſelf, nor by any authority of the Church or See of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by any other means, with any other, hath any Power or authority to depoſe the King, or to diſpoſe of any of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties kingdoms or dominions, or to authoriſe any foraign Prince to invade or annoy him or his Countries, or to diſcharge any of his ſubjects of their allegiance and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Majeſty, or to give licence or leave to any of them to bear arms, raiſe rumults, or to offer any violence or hurt to his Majeſties Royall Perſon, State, or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to any of his Majeſtyes ſubjects within his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Dominions.</p>
            <p>Where it is obſerved, that the intent of the Oath, is to ſecure the King of the inviolable right and ſafety of his Government of the obedience and allegiance of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt attempts of depoſition by his ſubjects againſt Rebellion and taking up Armes by his ſubjects againſt him, as alſo againſt forraign invaſions; and the ſaid Oath declares, that the Subjects cannot be authoriſed unto theſe undutifull and diſloyall practices againſt the King, neither by the <hi>Pope</hi> nor any other with him (and therefore it is ſuppoſed and implyed) not by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without him, which inferrs thus much, that none, neither the <hi>Pope,</hi> nor See of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor any other, hath any Power to depoſe the King, to diſpoſe of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or to diſcharge the Subjects of their obedience or allegiance to his Majeſty, or to give licence or leave to any of them whoſoever they are, either ſingle or together to do that which it is ſuppoſed <hi>â fortiori,</hi> without ſuch licenſe, they have no Power of themſelves to do: <hi>viz.</hi> to bear Armes, raiſe Tumules, or to offer any violence or hurt to his Majeſties Royall Perſon, State or Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereby this Oath, and therein the Conſcience of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106525:11"/>Nation, doth upon ſo dreadfull an Obligation diſclaime and diſavow all Power, to depoſe the Kings of this Nation in any whatſoever. As alſo all taking up Armes, Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and Diſobedience againſt him; as wicked and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and contrary to the allegiance of Subjects, which is aſſerted in this Oath: nor is it imaginable that the intent of thoſe that made this Oath, For the ſecurity of the King and his Government did mean, that themſelves or any others in their capacity ſhould take upon them the wicked pretence of any ſuch power, which they do here ſo much abominate in the <hi>Pope</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> V That the Subjects of this Kingdome in this Oath, do ſwear from their heart, not to admit of any Abſolution of themſelves from their obedience to the King, but (as the very words of the Oath import) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any abſolution of the ſaid ſubjects from their Obedience (who ever they he that ſhould take upon them to give it them, much leſſe is it to be ſuppoſed, that they can Abſolve themſelves) to bear Faith and true Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to his Majeſty, and not onely to him in being, but to his Heirs and Succeſſors; and the world knows who it is that the Law and Cuſtome of this Nation ſtates to be the Heir and Succeſſor of the King, even the eldeſt Son of the Predeceſſor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> VI. That this National Oath, doth binde the people of this Nation, in the very expreſſe words thereof, to defend Him and Them (that is, the King and his Heirs and Succeſſors, immediately before mentioned) to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of their power (words of a very ſevere and exact importance, admitting of no negligence, coldneſs, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes) againſt all Conſpiracies and Attempt whatſoever, (mark and tremble to think how this hath been violated) which ſhall be made againſt His or Their Perſons, their Crown and Dignity; by reaſon or colour of any ſuch ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or declaration (as is before mentioned of the Pope or See of <hi>Rome</hi>) or otherwiſe, which doth expreſſely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liege the ſubjects to appear for the defence of the King, of his Perſon and Government, againſt all attempts, againſt them by any whatſoever, or upon any pretences ſoever.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106525:12"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Ob.</hi> VII. That the people of this Nation are highly obliged in the importance of this Oath with their beſt endeavour to diſcloſe, and make known unto his Majeſty (in being) &amp; to his Heirs and Succeſſors, all Treaſons and Traiterous conſpiracies, that they ſhall know or hear of, to be againſt the King, or any of his Heirs and Succeſſors: Where the conſpiracies which are againſt the King and his Succeſſors have the ſtile of Treaſons and Traiterous conſpiracies, for the Epithite or Title or Traiterous is not to be underſtood as a mark of diſtinction, but of aggravation; &amp; all ſuch the people of this land are bound by thi Oath to reveal unto the King &amp; his Succeſſors, with their beſt endeavor when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they hear of them, or have any knowledge of them, to the intent, without all doubt, that they may be preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and the contrivers and actors brought to condigne puniſhment: and therefore all concealing of ſuch things, and much more all centriving, and acting of them, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with them, or abetting of them, is groſs perjury a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Oath, as well as treaſon againſt the King, and his Heirs and ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> VIII. That in this Oath the people do with this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred obligation profeſs, an hearty abhorring, deteſting, and abjuration of that doctrine and poſition, as impious, hereticall and damnable; that princes which be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated and deprived by the <hi>Pope,</hi> may be depoſed and murthered by their Subjects, or any other whatſoever; which doth undoubtedly diſclaime and abjure all depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and murthering of Kings by their Subjects or others, as a practice, as impious, heretical, and damnable as any ſuch Doctrine, whether they be excommunicated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived by the <hi>Pope,</hi> or no: Unleſſe any ſhall be ſo mad and wicked as to think that their Kings may be murthered or depoſed by them or others, becauſe they are not excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated or deprived by the Pope, as if Princes ſtood in need of the Popes deprivation or exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication to ſecure them from depoſition, or being murthered by their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; &amp; then it is obvious enough to any mans conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how ſad and deſperate, how impious, heretical, damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106525:12"/>and perjurious againſt the faith and Oath of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: The miſtake and miſcarriage of ſome hath been of late (who would have been therein alſo examples unto others) and thoſe too I think, that took this very Oath, who inſtead of abjuring the depoſing and murthering of the King, have abjured the King himſelf, &amp; thereby (with a monſter of wickedneſs) have ſworn down the awful &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, their own Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant binding them to the Kings poſterity; the Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on binding to maintain and defend, according to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Allegiance, together with the Laws of God and man, and all that not onely juſtice and righteouſneſs, but even mercy, compaſſion, and gratitude, and thankfulneſs, which bindeth the people of this land unto his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>And withall it may be full eaſily diſcovered, in the view of this Oath, how wickedly forward ſome inſtruments and factours of the Jeſuites amongſt us, that thought not ſit to ſtay for a ſentence of excommunication or depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Pope, but have acted theſe horrid things without it, that they have done, to the reproach of the Chriſtian profeſſion, and the ſhame and ſcandal of the proteſtant Religion, and of this Nation; I am ſorry that it is become ſo neceſſary as it is, to deal ſo plainly with them in this matter; but it is of great concernment unto them, and us in order to their ſalvation, that they ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed of their miſcarriage, that we may not own their guilt by our ſilence, when the world doth ſomuch cry out againſt them, and that they may, if it be poſſibly, repent, and be ſaved, which I do earneſtly beg of the Lord for them.</p>
            <p>IX. Obſerve, that this national Oath, doth abſolutely diſclaim all power in the Pope, or in any other to abſolve the people from this Oath, or any part thereof, and doth renounce all pardons, and diſpenſations to the contrary, as alſo all equivocation or mental reſervation whatſoever, and all this upon the engagement of the true faith of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106525:13"/>
            <p> Laſtly obſerve, that in that dreadfull expreſſion in the cloſe of both theſe Oaths, <hi>So help me God,</hi> which is uttered with the hand upon the Goſpel, and ſealed, as it were, with kiſſing that holy Book, our Intereſt in Gods help and Salvation by the Goſpel is, as it were pawned and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for out fidelity therein. By all this then that hath been ſaid, it is clear and evident how highly the people of this Nation are engaged, to perform all the duties of theſe Oaths unto the preſent King: How wicked thoſe actions have been, that have been managed againſt his Father and himſelf? What a ſad guilt of perjury there is upon this Nation? And how neceſſary it is, there ſhould be a publick Humiliation for this, as well as for other grievous ſins in this Nation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106525:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
